A Guide to the Snyder Family Papers, ca. 1850-1901: SC 0204
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Snyder Family Papers,
ca. 1850-1901
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Snyder Family
SC 0204
.3 cubic feet; 3 boxes
The Snyder Family Papers, ca. 1850-1901, comprise two account books and photographs documenting the John Snyder family of Augusta County, Virginia.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research. Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection. Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the James Madison University Special Collections Library to use this collection.
Acquisition Information
The ledgers and photo album were purchased September 17, 2011 at the Mt. Solon, Virginia estate sale of Charles Weekley. Weekley's real estate and personal property were sold by auctioneer Charley Whetzel.
Biographical Information
The ledgers provide very little concrete information about John Snyder except for that he was a blacksmith most likely living in the Augusta County area during the 1850s and 1860s. The 1860 census lists a J. Snyder living in Augusta County who is married to S. Snyder, with two children: W. H. and J. A. Snyder. The 1860 census, along with the 1899 Augusta County Business Directory, also lists J. Snyder as a blacksmith. Additionally, a genealogy site documenting the Sheets family of Pennsylvania, Virginia, and Iowa references a John Snyder who was born in 1824 and died after 1900 in Augusta County. This John Snyder was married to his cousin, Sarah Sheetz, in March 1849, and together they had four children: William H. Snyder (b. 1849), Joseph A. Snyder (b. 1851), Martin Snyder (b. 1861), and Lewis J. Snyder (b. 1863). The genealogy site also mentions that John worked as a blacksmith as well as a farmer. All of this information is consistent with the business directory, census records, and dates of the ledgers.
The Snyder family photo album originally included a sheet of paper that records the date of death of a John Snyder on February 7, 1901, a date that correlates with the information above. This document is retained in the collection. A few of the photographs inside of the album contain captions such as "Uncle John," "Lewis Snyder," and "Cousin Martin Snyder," indicating that the album may have been owned by a sibling or cousin of John or Sarah Snyder.
Scope and Content
The Snyder Family Papers, ca. 1805-1901, comprise two account books and photographs documenting the John Snyder (variously spelled Snider) family of Augusta County. Snyder was a blacksmith operating out of Parnassus in Augusta County, Virginia. Surnames recorded in the ledgers include Showalter, Moyer, Miller, Shumate, and Huffman.
The 46 photographs in the collection include albumen prints, collodion prints, gelatin developing-out paper, and tintypes. All of the photos are black and white or sepia in color, and most are accompanied by a matte frame or a decorative paper sleeve. The photographs are housed individually and are arranged in the original order they were found in upon removal from the photo album. There are presumably images of John Snyder and two of his children in this collection. Notations by said photograph refer to him as "Uncle John." There is also an obituary for John A. Marshall, whose children are included in the images and are referred to as cousins. From the little amount of information available, it is possible that the album was owned by a sister of John Snyder who married into the Marshall family, or perhaps a child of said sister.
Arrangement
The ledgers are housed in a custom box and arranged chronologically. During initial processing in 2011, the photographs were each assigned a unique identification number based on their original collection number P0004 and according to their original order in the now discarded photo album. They are arranged accordingly. Three photographs are housed in a separate folder due to their larger size.
Bibliography
1860 United States Census, Augusta County, Virginia. http://www.shambaugh.org/1860VA.htm (Accessed 14 Nov. 2011).
Directory of the Representative Business and Professional Men of Augusta County and Staunton. Rohrer & Diamond, 1899. http://files.usgwarchives.net/va/augusta/misc/1899biz-m-z.txt (Accessed 14 Nov. 2011).
"Sheets Family of Pennsylvania, Virginia, and Iowa." http://annasheets.brinkster.net/sheets.htmljohn (Accessed 14 Nov. 2011).
Index Terms
Subjects:
Snyder, John; Snyder family; Blacksmiths -- Virginia -- Records and correspondence; Account books -- Sources; Business records -- Sources; Virginia -- History, Local -- Sources
Genre and Form Terms:
Account books; Photographs
- Ledger, 1849-1859 (Box 1)
- Ledger, 1858-1865 (Box 2)
- Photographs, ca. 1850-1900 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - P0004.01.001, ca. 1885-1900
    Scope and Content
    Black and white, full-body front view portrait of a man and a woman; the man sits in a chair with the woman standing just behind his right shoulder. Most likely a collodion print attached to white cardboard with a gilded edge. Photographer: Lively, East Main Street, McMinnville, Tennessee.
  - P0004.01.002, March 5, 1892
    An albumen print of a full-body front view portrait of a man and a woman posing in front of a rustic backdrop. The man sits with the woman standing by his right shoulder. Photo album caption identifies man to be "Luis Snyder." Print is attached to cream colored cardboard with a gilded edge. Photographer: J. M. Hill, Bridgewater, Virginia.
  - P0004.01.003, ca. 1885-1900
    Black and white, full body front view of two young, finely dressed children playing in a dirt road; a young boy pulls a toddler in a small wagon. Most likely a collodion print attached to cream colored cardboard.
  - P0004.01.004, ca. 1855-1900
    Black and white, almost full body front view portrait of a young man sitting in a chair and resting his arm on a table. Photo album caption identifies man to be "Uncle John." Tintype housed in a white paper sleeve with an ornate red border.
  - P0004.01.005, ca. 1855-1900
    Sepia, waist-up front view of a man that is looking directly into the camera. Photo album caption identifies him to be "Uncle Frank." Most likely an albumen print attached to thin cream-colored cardboard.
  - P0004.01.006, ca. 1855-1900
    Black and white, front view portrait of a young boy who is looking into the camera. A red bowtie seems to be colored/drawn in to the photo. "Luis Snyder" written in pencil on the back of the encasing, and a photo album caption also reads "Mother's half brothers." Tintype housed in a tan paper sleeve with an ornate red border, and a piece of lined notebook paper glued to the back.
  - P0004.01.007, ca. 1855-1900
    Black and white, front view portrait of a man who is looking into the camera. Photo album caption underneath read "Mother's half brothers." Tintype housed in an embellished white paper sleeve.
  - P0004.01.008, ca. 1855-1900
    Black and white, front view portrait of a man and a woman, who is holding an open book. This image was also housed above the photo album caption "Mother's half brothers." Most likely an albumen print attached to thin cream-colored cardboard. Photographer: T. L. Darnell, Cumberland, Maryland.
  - P0004.01.009, ca. 1885-1900
    Black and white, shoulders-up front view portrait of two young women. "Rena" written in pencil on the back. Most likely a collodion print attached to thick black cardboard.
  - P0004.01.010, ca. 1885-1900
    Black and white, front view of a man sitting in between two women in front of a stone brick building. Caption on the back reads "my bachelor son and two of his cousins at Lincoln farm sitting on a part of the memorial building." Possibly printed on gelatin developing-out paper.
  - P0004.01.011, ca. 1885-1900
    Black and white, shoulders-up front view of a young woman looking to the right of the camera and wearing a very ornate hat. Most likely a collodion print attached to small piece of cardboard that is cut with a gilded edge.
  - P0004.01.012, ca. 1855-1900
    Black and white, shoulders-up front view of a young boy who is looking into the camera. Photo album caption identifies him as "John." Tintype housed in an embellished cream-colored paper sleeve.
  - P0004.01.013, ca. 1855-1900
    Black and white, shoulders-up front view of an elderly man who is looking into the camera. Photo album caption identifies him as "Father." Tintype housed in an embellished cream-colored paper sleeve.
  - P0004.01.014, ca. 1855-1900
    Black and white, front view portrait of a very young girl who is shyly looking into the camera. Photo album caption identifies her as "Irena." Tintype housed in a white paper sleeve with a red border that is badly stained.
  - P0004.01.015, ca. 1855-1900
    Black and white, front view portrait of a young boy sitting who is looking into the camera and sitting in a chair. "John" written in pencil on the front of the paper sleeve. Tintype housed in a white paper sleeve with a red border that is badly stained.
  - P0004.01.016, ca. 1855-1900
    Black and white, front view portrait of a young man who is looking into the camera. "John" is written in pencil on the front of the paper sleeve. Tintype housed in an orange paper sleeve with an ornate red border.
  - P0004.01.017, ca. 1855-1900
    Black and white, front view portrait of a young girl. The flowers of the bow on the front of her dress seemed to be colored in red or pink. "Irena" is written in pencil on the front of the paper sleeve. Tintype housed in a cream-colored paper sleeve with a red border.
  - P0004.01.018, ca. 1850-1900
    Small card with an illustration of a bird, flowers, and small house with the inscription "With God all things are possible. Matth. 19-26." "From Pattie Marshall" is written in pencil on the back.
  - P0004.01.019, ca. 1855-1900
    Sepia, front view of a cow standing in a fenced-in area and looking into the camera. Possibly an albumen print attached to embellished gray cardboard.
  - P0004.01.020, ca. 1855-1900
    Sepia, front view portrait of a baby that is looking to the right of the camera. "Myrtle Genevieve Ekleberry 5 mo old" is written in pencil on the back. Most likely an albumen print attached to white cardboard with a gilded edge.
  - P0004.01.021, ca. 1855-1900
    Sepia, full-body front view portrait of a man and a woman that are dressed for a special occasion such as a wedding. Albumen print attached to embellished white cardboard. Photographer: Shellabarger, Horton, Kansas.
  - P0004.01.022, ca. 1885-1900
    Black and white, full-body front view of a young female toddler who is looking to the left of the camera. Collodion print attached to black cardboard. Photographer: Shellabarger, Horton, Kansas.
  - P0004.01.025, ca. 1855-1900
    Sepia, full-body front view portrait of a man sitting in a chair, with a woman standing to his left and resting her arm on his shoulder. Both are looking into the camera. Albumen print attached to pink cardboard with a gold border on the front. Photographer: B. A. Blakemore's Photo Art Gallery, Augusta Street, Staunton, Virginia.
  - P0004.01.026, ca. 1855-1900
    Sepia, front portrait view of a man with a full beard and mustache who is looking slightly to the right of the camera. Tintype housed in a white paper sleeve with an ornate red border.
  - P0004.01.027, ca. 1855-1900
    Sepia, full-body front view of a man sitting in a chair in front of a scenic backdrop. Tintype housed in a paper sleeve with cut corners and an ornate red border.
  - P0004.01.028, ca. 1855-1900
    Black and white, front view portrait of a man who is looking slightly to the right of the camera. "Cousin Joe Snyder" written in pencil on the back of the sleeve. Tintype housed in an embellished yellow and purple paper sleeve. Photographer: B. A. Blakemore's Photograph Gallery, No. 4 North Augusta Street, Staunton, Virginia.
  - P0004.01.029, ca. 1855-1900
    Sepia, silhouette portrait of a young woman with her hair ornately braided. Possibly an albumen print that is a copy of an older photograph, glued to a thin piece of tan cardboard. Photographer: Johnston's Star Gallery, Richland Center, Wisconsin.
  - P0004.01.030, ca. 1855-1900
    Sepia, full-body portrait of an elderly man sitting in a chair and an elderly woman, who is standing next to the man with her hand resting on his shoulder. Albumen print glued to a thin piece of tan cardboard.
  - P0004.01.031, ca. 1855-1900
    Black and white, front view portrait of a young man who is looking slightly to the right of the camera. Most likely an albumen print glued to a thin piece of tan cardboard with a red border. Photographer: Johnston's Star Gallery, Richland Center, Wisconsin.
  - P0004.01.032, ca. 1855-1900
    Black and white, front view portrait of a middle-aged man who is looking slightly to the right of the camera. Photo album caption identifies him as "Father." Tintype housed in a a paper sleeve that is orange with an ornate red border on the front, and purple on the back. Photographer: B. A. Blakemore's Photographic Gallery, Augusta Street, Staunton, Virginia.
  - P0004.01.033, ca. 1855-1900
    Black and white, front view of a woman sitting in front of an elaborate backdrop. Photo album caption identifies her as "Mother." Tintype.
  - P0004.01.034, ca. 1855-1900
    Sepia, front view of a man who is smiling and looking into the camera. Albumen print attached to peach-colored cardboard. Photographer: Locke, Richland Center, Wisconsin.
  - P0004.01.035, February 20, 1882
    Black and white, front view of a young woman who is sitting and looking into the camera. Photo album caption identifies her as "Sister," and the date is written in pencil on the back. Tintype housed in a white paper sleeve with an ornate gold border.
  - P0004.01.036, ca. 1855-1900
    Black and white, front view of a boy who is looking into the camera. Photo album caption identifies him as "John." Tintype housed in a tan-grey colored paper sleeve with a pink back, and an ornate gold border.
  - P0004.01.037, ca. 1855-1900
    Black and white, front view of a young man looking slightly to the left of the camera. Tintype housed in an embellished light pink paper sleeve.
  - P0004.01.038, ca. 1885-1900
    Black and white, front view of a woman who is looking to the right of the camera. Most likely a collodion print attached to green, cream, and gold cardboard. Photographer: W. J. Hillman, Richland Center, Wisconsin.
  - P0004.01.039, ca. 1855-1900
    Black and white, front view portrait of a man who is looking to the right of the camera. Tintype housed in an orange paper sleeve with an ornate red border.
  - P0004.01.040, ca. 1885-1900
    Black and white, full-body front view portrait of a man and a woman who are looking into the camera; the man sits in a chair while the woman stands to his life, with her hand on his shoulder. They both stand in front of an elaborate backdrop. "Miss E. I. Snyder" written in blue ink on the back.Most likely a collodion print attached to green and gold cardboard. Photographer: W. J. Hillman, Richland Center, Wisconsin.
  - P0004.01.041, ca. 1855-1900
    Black and white, front view portrait of a young man who is sitting and looking to the right of the camera. Photo album caption identifies him as "Lewis Snyder." Tintype housed in a white paper sleeve with an ornate red border. Photographer: B. A. Blakemore's Photograph Gallery, Staunton, Virginia.
  - P0004.01.042, ca. 1855-1900
  - P0004.01.043, ca. 1855-1900
    Black and white, full-body front view portrait of a man sitting in a chair in front of a scenic backdrop and looking into the camera. Photo album caption identifies him as "Cousin Martin Snyder." Tintype.
  - P0004.01.044, ca. 1885-1900
    Black and white, full-body portrait of a woman standing next to and resting her left hand on a chair. Most likely a collodion print attached to a piece of stained cardboard with a gold border.
  - P0004.01.045, ca. 1885-1900
    Black and white, full-body portrait of a woman sitting on a bench with a young girl standing to her right and a young boy standing to her left. All three are posed in front of a scenic backdrop. "Belongs to Abr. & T. Paschal" written in pencil on the back. Most likely a collodion print attached to stained white cardboard with gold trim at the bottom.
  - P0004.01.046, ca. 1885-1900
    Black and white, front view portrait of a man who is looking to the left of the camera. Most likely a collodion print attached to green cardboard with a gold border. Photographer: W. J. Hillman, Richland Center, Wisconsin.
- Photographs, ca .1885-1900 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - P0004.01.018a, Probably 1898
    Black and white, full-body front view of a baby girl who is looking to the left of the camera. "Miss Ellen Vogel, aged 8 months Aug 3 1898" is written in pencil on the back. Collodion print attached to cream-colored cardboard. Photographer: Mrs. W. D. Hughes, McMinnville, Tennessee.
  - P0004.01.023, ca. 1885-1900
    Black and white, front view portrait of a man who is looking slightly to the left of the camera. Photo album caption identifies him as "Cousin Burnet Marshall Lill's brother." Collodion print attached to dark grey cardboard.
  - P0004.01.024, ca. 1885-1900
    Black and white, front view portrait of a man and a woman that are sitting and looking to the right of the camera, while a very young girl stands in between them with her hands on each of their shoulders and looking into the camera. Photo album caption identifies the woman as "Lill Marshall Wilson." Collodion print attached to dark grey cardboard.
- Loose papers, 1880-ca. 1901, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - P0004.01.001a, ca. 1880-1900
    A piece of paper housed behind P0004.01.001 in the photo album. "J O, G A E" written in pencil.
  - P0004.01.047, after 1901
    A piece of notepad paper that was placed behind the front cover of the photo album. Contains information about the deaths of various Snyder family members.
  - P0004.01.048, 1897, undated
    Two photocopied obituaries. One documents the life and death of John A. Marshall (1828-1897) and the second announces the death of John F. Snider.
  - P0004.01.049, undated
    Photocopied marriage announcements. One documents the wedding of F. J. Marshall and Lizzie Mauzy and the second announces the wedding of Thomas Hildebrand to Maggie Newman.